<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN"
        "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EMLC</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Early Modern Low Countries</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="epub">2543-1587</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Stichting EMLC, supported by Utrecht University Library Open Access Journals
                </publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">emlc.10908</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.51750/emlc.10908</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Popular Song Topics in the Dutch Republic: A Data-Driven Study into Topical Fluctuations
                    in the Dutch Song Database (1550-1750)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Lassche</surname>
                        <given-names>Alie</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <bio>
                        <p>
                            <bold>Alie Lassche</bold>
                            is a PhD candidate in Dutch History at Leiden University within the project &#x2018;Chronicling
                            Novelty. New knowledge in the Netherlands, 1500-1850&#x2019;. She investigates the changing
                            mediascape of Dutch chroniclers, using both qualitative and quantitative methods to analyse
                            a corpus of about three hundred early modern Dutch chronicles. In 2019, she was awarded her
                            research master&#x2019;s degree in Dutch literature and culture at Utrecht University with
                            distinction. In her research, she applies computational methods to historical text corpora,
                            in order to investigate cultural changes over time.
                        </p>
                    </bio>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2022</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>6</volume>
            <issue>2</issue>
            <fpage>253</fpage>
            <lpage>277</lpage>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright: copyright is retained by the authors</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
                <license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" license-type="open-access">
                    <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                        International License.
                    </license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri xlink:href="https://www.emlc-journal.org/articles/10.51750/emlc.10908"/>
            <abstract>
                <p>This article investigates popular topics and topical fluctuations in a diachronic corpus of 43,772
                    Dutch songs, all written between 1550 and 1750, contained within the Dutch Song Database.
                    Computational methods such as topic modelling are used to analyse the relationship between topical
                    changes and cultural-historical developments. Two cultural trends are used as case studies: the role
                    of Petrarchism, and the articulation of a patriotic identity in early modern Dutch song culture.
                    Furthermore, this data-driven approach reveals how subcategories can be defined within the existing
                    but incomplete genre classification in the song collection. The results obtained contribute to a
                    better understanding of the richness of the Dutch Song Database, and will facilitate the use of the
                    song collection by future users.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>song culture</kwd>
                <kwd>topic modelling</kwd>
                <kwd>topical fluctuations</kwd>
                <kwd>text mining</kwd>
                <kwd>digital humanities</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <p>During the early modern period, the tradition of the monodic song in the vernacular remained extremely strong
            in the Dutch Republic. Tens of thousands of Dutch songs were written, published, read, and, obviously, sung.
            Young and old, rich and poor alike, were engaged in song culture, which was, according to Louis Peter Grijp,
            as typically Dutch as the culture of painting.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
                <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>
            According to Natascha Veldhorst, singing was second nature to the Dutch: everyone sang anywhere and at any
            time.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">
                <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>
            Traces of this practice can be found not only in contemporary paintings, but also in archives and libraries,
            where hundreds of early modern Dutch songbooks are still kept. The singing tradition flourished especially
            in the seventeenth century. Previous studies have already shown that singing was a social business in the
            early modern Low Countries; people usually sang together and children were taught to sing in school. Singing
            and music lessons had been a common part of the curriculum from the sixteenth century, as <italic>musica
            </italic> was considered one of the <italic>artes liberales</italic>. Even those who could not read music
            were able to take part: the use of the contrafactum (writing new lyrics on existing melodies) made it
            possible for such singers to learn new songs anyway.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">
                <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>
        </p>
        <p>But what did people sing about during early modern times? And what changes in song topics can we observe over
            a long period of time? For decades, literary scholars have published studies on historical songs, their
            topics, the public, and their function in society. Eddy Grootes, for instance, has analysed the rise in
            popularity of certain songbooks for youngsters in the first quarter of the seventeenth century.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">
                <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>
            Els Stronks has researched early modern songs written by and for youngsters, demonstrating how songs played
            a role in the identity formation of the early modern Dutch youth.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">
                <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>
            Furthermore, she has argued how songs were used to transmit knowledge.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">
                <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>
            The most famous Dutch song from the early modern period was chosen to be the national anthem of the
            Netherlands in 1932. This song &#x2013; the <italic>Wilhelmus</italic> &#x2013; is without doubt the most
            researched song in Dutch history, not least because the identity of its composer was shrouded in mystery for
            many years. This mystery was finally solved in 2017 through stylometrics, in the notable study <italic>Van
                wie is het Wilhelmus?
            </italic> (&#x2018;Who wrote the <italic>Wilhelmus</italic>?&#x2019;).
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">
                <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>
        </p>
        <p>Although many authors have studied the topics of early modern songs, their research was always based on case
            studies. Using such methodology does not enable the researcher to search for patterns that occur over a
            longer period of time. Quantitative studies on early modern songs are in fact scarce, and this scarcity is
            closely related to the supposed lack of data, a problem already observed by Veldhorst. In her work on Dutch
            early modern songbooks, she noted that it was hard to come up with specific numbers regarding early modern
            song production. In the first place, there is no overview of those early modern songbooks currently held in
            European libraries. Secondly, one has to keep in mind that songbooks were heavily modified, expanded, and
            revised over the course of time. Thirdly, the small survival chances of the songbook further complicate any
            attempt at estimating the number of songs that were printed at the time.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">
                <sup>8</sup>
            </xref>
            And if there are two things you need in order to perform quantitative research, it is numbers and data.
        </p>
        <p>While we may lack comprehensive data sets on early modern Dutch songs, that does not mean we have no
            representative data at all. In the early nineties, the musicologist Louis Grijp undertook an impressive and
            successful attempt to map Dutch early modern song culture. In his 1991 dissertation he reconstructed the
            melodies of songs by finding their sources and analysing their reception. One of the results of his
            extensive work was the birth of the so-called <italic>voetenbank</italic>, an electronic database containing
            data on melodies, verses, and stanzas of (at the time) 5,700 Dutch historical songs.
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">
                <sup>9</sup>
            </xref>
            Almost thirty years after Grijp&#x2019;s dissertation, his database has developed into an extensive Dutch
            Song Database, containing metadata of more than 175,000 Dutch songs. Furthermore, in the last couple of
            decades the techniques for digital exploration of a corpus have become more advanced. This article shows how
            making full use of these new techniques can allow for meaningful quantitative research into early modern
            Dutch songs and how their dominant topics changed over time. I have established what topics dominated early
            modern Dutch songs by performing topic modelling &#x2013; a way to identify the topics that occur in a
            collection of documents &#x2013; on a corpus of 43,772 Dutch songs from the period 1550-1750.
        </p>
        <p>The aims of this article are manifold. Firstly, it aims at contributing to a better understanding of the
            richness of the Dutch Song Database. At the point of writing, it lacks comprehensive metadata &#x2013; an
            example being information regarding song genre, which makes the search for songs of a specific genre a
            frustrating task. The results published in this article may therefore serve to increase the database&#x2019;s
            usability for future researchers. Secondly, through two case studies I will analyse the dynamics which can
            be observed in the fluctuation of dominant topics over time, and suggest how these changes in topical
            distributions can be related to the cultural-historical context in which they occur. Finally, I wish to
            demonstrate how this methodology can contribute to further research into early modern Dutch songs, and,
            indeed, into other textual genres.
        </p>
        <p>Although I am, in this study, using methods never before applied to early modern songs, I also rely heavily
            on previous, qualitative, research into early modern Dutch song culture. The two cases discussed in more
            detail are well known from existing studies: the role of Petrarchism in early modern Dutch songs, and the
            way in which songs were used to articulate a patriotic identity &#x2013; with the <italic>Wilhelmus</italic> being
            perhaps the classic example. To explore how these two cases can be related to the results of a quantitative
            approach to researching Dutch song culture, I use a sample of the Dutch Song Database, containing songs from
            1550-1750. The article begins by offering a historical background of the two cases. The second section will
            discuss the corpus and its characteristics in more detail, the third section the methods I have employed,
            and the two subsequent sections contain my results. The article concludes with an evaluation of how the
            combination of qualitative and quantitative methods can enlarge our knowledge of early modern song culture.
        </p>
        <sec id="s1">
            <title>Petrarchism and Patriotism in Dutch Songs</title>
            <p>The starting point of my first case study is that the poetry of early modern Dutch poets became
                increasingly embedded in a Renaissance and classical tradition. Inspired by the manner in which Italian
                and French writers adapted the traditions of Greek and Latin poetry, Dutch poets also appropriated their
                topics and genres. An important example of this embedding in the Renaissance tradition was the practice
                of the Petrarchan genre. The Italian Renaissance poet Francesco Petrarca &#x2013; or Petrarch, as he is
                known in English &#x2013; was a fourteenth-century Italian poet, whose fame extended beyond his country&#x2019;s
                own borders already during his lifetime.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">
                    <sup>10</sup>
                </xref>
                One of the reasons for Petrarch&#x2019;s fame was the popularity of his love poetry. His love sonnets
                were distinguished by the worship of a charming but unreachable woman, which meant that love always
                causes both happiness and pain in his poems. The physical beauty of the beloved is often described using
                natural metaphors and mythological references. The lover is often characterized as someone with a split
                personality, who struggles with suicidal tendencies.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">
                    <sup>11</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>In his study on seventeenth-century songbooks for youngsters, Grootes argues that one would not expect
                Petrarchism to become popular in the Low Countries, since the trope of the unreachable woman was
                paradoxical to the actual surplus of women in Amsterdam and the province of Holland at the time:
                &#x2018;At first sight, there seems to be no ground for the humbly pleading of the lovers, nor for the
                presentation of the songbooks as instruments to make the girls a little more obliging.&#x2019;<xref
                        ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">
                    <sup>12</sup>
                </xref>
                Even so, Grootes suggests that the ideology of Petrarchism, with its emphasis on restraint and the lack
                of sexual boldness, probably fitted perfectly with the marriage policy advocated by the parents.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">
                    <sup>13</sup>
                </xref>
                He also cites the literary scholar August Keersmaekers, who has argued that the songbook <italic>Den
                    Nieuwen Lust-hof
                </italic> (1602) could be interpreted as part of &#x2018;a culture of piety propagated and imposed from
                above&#x2019;, in opposition to the older songbooks.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">
                    <sup>14</sup>
                </xref>
                The quantitative methods used in this study are ideally suited to explore whether the popularity of the
                classic genres, and the Petrarchan genre in particular, can be found in the current research corpus.
                Furthermore, qualitative research has not paid attention to the moment of decline in popularity of these
                genres, something which the methodology used in this study might also shed light.
            </p>
            <p>Another claim that will be tested in this study is how songs were used to articulate a feeling of
                patriotism. As Cornelis van der Haven notes, a long tradition of aggressive patriotic rhetoric can be
                found in Dutch literature, a tradition that is strongly related to the Dutch liberation myth of the
                struggle against Habsburg Spain that would be constructed in later centuries.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">
                    <sup>15</sup>
                </xref>
                In times of war or political crisis, feelings of patriotism and unity are aroused and propagated by,
                among others, poems and songs.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">
                    <sup>16</sup>
                </xref>
                A social activity, singing together created a feeling of belonging to a particular group, and
                contributed to the formation and maintenance of a social identity and an imagined community.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">
                    <sup>17</sup>
                </xref>
                Regarding the early modern Netherlands, Dieuwke van der Poel, Louis Grijp, and Wim van Anrooij have
                distinguished seven singing groups. The &#x2018;political group&#x2019; is most relevant in this
                context, which they describe as a group &#x2018;(often with a specific religious affiliation) such as
                the anti-Catholic and anti-Spanish <italic>Geuzen</italic> (&#x2018;Beggars&#x2019;)&#x2019;.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">
                    <sup>18</sup>
                </xref>
                Their protest songs &#x2013; known as beggar songs &#x2013; became very popular in the late sixteenth
                century. Initially they were published and disseminated via broadsheets, but before long they were
                bundled together and published in a songbook called <italic>Nieu Geusen Liedtboexcken</italic> (The New
                Beggars&#x2019; Songbook). The oldest edition of this song book dates from 1577, and several reprints
                were published in subsequent years. The songs were intended as inflammatory news announcements that
                would encourage revolt.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">
                    <sup>19</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>Songbooks were the most obvious way to articulate an identity, in other words, to express one&#x2019;s
                belonging to a group. Often group identity was already prominent in the title, for example in the
                <italic>Nieu Geusen liedtboecxken.</italic>
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">
                    <sup>20</sup>
                </xref>
                Furthermore, identity was also articulated through song lyrics &#x2013; which is something I will
                explore in this article. Although the <italic>Wilhelmus</italic> is the most well-known of all beggar
                songs, and one which retained both its political overtone and signalling function long after the 1648
                Peace of M&#x00FC;nster, there were many other songs.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">
                    <sup>21</sup>
                </xref>
                While their popularity probably did not reach the height of the current Dutch national anthem, their
                tropes of nation and identity likely resonated with the inhabitants of the Dutch Republic. That being
                said, there were also songs expressing love for the fatherland without specific political orientation,
                in which the whole Dutch nation was addressed as one political group, especially in times of war. During
                the seventeenth century, patriotic ideas became more widespread, a movement which was not only down to
                the beggars and their repertoire. Orthodox Protestant ministers also started to elaborate on the idea
                that God, the Netherlands, and the House of Orange were inextricably connected.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">
                    <sup>22</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2">
            <title>The Dutch Song Database</title>
            <p>To test whether these trends can be found in a larger research corpus, I have relied on the Dutch Song
                Database, which contains the metadata of approximately 175,000 songs in the Dutch language, from the
                Middle Ages up to the twentieth century. The database was initiated in the early 1990s by Louis Grijp,
                who continued to lead its development until 2015. During these years, many research and documentation
                projects have been carried out, and so an enormous amount of high-quality data has been collected.
                Nowadays, the Dutch Song Database offers a rich cross-section of Dutch song culture throughout history.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">
                    <sup>23</sup>
                </xref>
                It contains several genres, including love songs, satirical songs, psalms and other religious songs,
                folksongs, and children&#x2019;s songs. For every song, the source for the text and/or the melody are
                indicated. Other available metadata include the author&#x2019;s name (if known), the first line, the
                number of stanzas, genre, melody, stanza form, and number of verses. In addition, the results of the
                project Dutch Songs On Line became available in 2014.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">
                    <sup>24</sup>
                </xref>
                The project has made 53,351 full song texts accessible online. Of these texts, 29,590 have had both
                their lyrics and metadata encoded with <sc>tei</sc> compliant <sc>xml</sc>, which provides the
                publication date, geographical location, melody, and genre. For the purposes of this study, I have
                limited this sample to songs that were printed and published between 1550 and 1750, which resulted in a
                corpus of 22,297 songs. This number does not yet include the reprints and appearances of these songs in
                other songbooks. Since I wish to examine which song topics were more prevalent than others, it is
                necessary to include these data as well. Although the number of different lyrics will remain the same,
                the distribution of the songs can change. Suppose, for example, that songs on politics and history,
                which are not very prominent in the corpus based on the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tb001">tab.
                    1</xref>, are reprinted so often that their number increases massively, while songs on love are
                rarely reprinted. This would influence the distribution of topics in such a way that political and
                historical topics are more dominant than love topics. Expanding the corpus with reprints resulted in a
                corpus of 43,772 songs.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">
                    <sup>25</sup>
                </xref>
                Their distribution over time is visualized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg001">fig. 1</xref>.
            </p>
            <table-wrap id="tb001">
                <label>Tab. 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Number of songs in the Dutch Song Database by category and average word length. N &#x003D;
                        22,297.
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Category</th>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Number of songs</th>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Average number of words per song</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">None</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">7017</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">300</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Religion</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">6914</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">323</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Love and sex</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">3261</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">219</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Seasons and annual events</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1033</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">296</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Formal genres</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">818</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">334</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Amusement</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">722</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">251</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Emotions</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">694</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">322</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Narratives</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">479</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">363</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Cycle of life</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">473</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">223</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Politics and history</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">300</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">478</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Groups</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">187</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">223</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Children</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">148</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">221</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Occasions</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">100</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">277</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Theatre</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">90</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">207</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Work</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">59</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">360</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Miscellaneous</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">91</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Source: Dutch Song Database.</p>
                </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <fig id="fg001" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Annual distribution of songs in the Dutch Song Database, 1550-1750. N &#x003D; 43,722.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig1.jpg"/>
            </fig>
            <p>
                <xref ref-type="table" rid="tb001">Tab. 1</xref>
                gives an overview of the distribution of songs over the various categories, as labelled in the Dutch
                Song Database.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">
                    <sup>26</sup>
                </xref>
                The majority of the songs fall into the category &#x2018;religion&#x2019;, followed at a distance by
                &#x2018;love and sex&#x2019; and &#x2018;seasons and annual events&#x2019;. One might ask why a study on
                topics in song lyrics is useful, given that data on categories already exist, but a closer look at <xref
                    ref-type="table" rid="tb001">tab. 1
            </xref> shows the necessity of such a study. Not only does the categorical division seem rather arbitrary,
                there are also more than seven thousand songs that have not been assigned to a specific category at all.
                As such, the available data do not give an accurate overview of the distribution of songs over genres.
                Moreover, the wide-ranging categories do not reveal how subdivisions within a category are distributed.
                Are all religious songs on the same aspects of religion? Does &#x2018;love and sex&#x2019; mean that
                some songs are on love, and others on sex? There is an important difference between a genre and a topic,
                since a genre can comprise many different topics. A song within the genre &#x2018;love and sex&#x2019;
                might be a tragic love song, but it could also be a happy, uplifting love song. A quantitative analysis
                of the songs, using topic modelling, can therefore offer useful information: it offers a more
                fine-grained classification of the different genres, and will allow the topical fluctuations over time
                to be made visible.
            </p>
            <p>
                <xref ref-type="table" rid="tb001">Tab. 1</xref>
                also provides information about the average song length within each genre. It shows that the average
                length of a song belonging to the genre &#x2018;religion&#x2019; is about one hundred words longer than
                a song belonging to the category &#x2018;love and sex&#x2019;. The most outstanding outlier is the genre
                &#x2018;politics and history&#x2019;, whose songs contain, on average, 478 words. The graphs in <xref
                    ref-type="fig" rid="fg002">fig. 2
            </xref> give a more detailed insight in the distribution of songs within a genre. For the twelve most
                popular genres, the number of words per song is plotted against their frequency.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">
                    <sup>27</sup>
                </xref>
                In general, all genres show a similar distribution: most songs contain between one hundred and three
                hundred words, with few songs boasting very long word counts. While the genres &#x2018;religion&#x2019;,
                &#x2018;love and sex&#x2019;, and the songs categorized with &#x2018;none&#x2019; show a similar
                distribution, the word length within the genre &#x2018;politics and history&#x2019; is more erratic.
                Compared to other genres, such as &#x2018;amusement&#x2019;, &#x2018;cycle of life&#x2019;, &#x2018;groups&#x2019;,
                and &#x2018;children&#x2019;, it shows a much wider spread in song lengths. It should be noted that in
                topic modelling the length of a text might influence its topic probabilities: because a long text
                contains more words, chances are it contains more topics than a short text.
            </p>
            <fig id="fg002" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Song lengths by genre in the Dutch Song Database. N &#x003D; 22,297.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig2.jpg"/>
            </fig>
            <p>One consequence of the piecemeal, project-based process through which this database has been constructed
                is a skewed representation of certain epochs. For example, while every Dutch monophonic song dated
                before 1600 and known to exist is included in the database, coverage of later periods is less complete.
                We also have to take into account that there is likely a genre bias to be uncovered in the compilation
                of songbooks &#x2013; songs did not have similar chances of survival. Another drawback is that even when
                all known songs from a certain area are entered in the database, this probably is just a snippet of all
                songs that have been produced during that time. We can assume that a large fraction of the early modern
                song production is nowadays unknown to us, either because the documents no longer exist, or because they
                have not been recovered yet. Furthermore, the survival chances of a printed song are considered to be
                higher than that of a song in manuscript, and that of eighteenth-century song higher than that of a
                sixteenth-century song. In recent years, scholars have further explored to what extent the level of loss
                of historic works can be estimated. Leo Egghe and Goran Proot, for example, have proposed a
                probabilistic model, based on the frequency with which retrieved copies of historic works survive.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">
                    <sup>28</sup>
                </xref>
                Mike Kestemont and Folgert Karsdorp have used an unseen species model from ecodiversity to estimate the
                survival rate of Middle Dutch chivalric epics.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">
                    <sup>29</sup>
                </xref>
                Although this article will not contribute to the study of survival chances of early modern songs, it is
                important to note that the corpus I have used is undoubtedly biased and incomplete. Furthermore, these
                biases potentially change over time, and in that case also have implications for a comparative analysis
                of topics over time.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">
                    <sup>30</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
            <title>Topic Modelling</title>
            <p>Topic modelling is a way of extrapolating backwards from a collection of documents to infer the
                discourses that might have generated them. It is assumed that each document in a collection of documents
                is constructed from a mix of some set of possible topics. A topic can be understood as a collection of
                words that have different probabilities of appearance in passages discussing the said topic. The model
                assigns high probabilities to words and sets of words that tend to co-occur in multiple contexts across
                the corpus. It must be noted that a topic is a probability distribution over the entire vocabulary, and
                that these distributions can vary hugely between topics. The ten most frequent words of one topic might
                together make up fifty percent of the topic, while the ten most frequent words of another topic only
                cover five percent of the topic. Although looking at the ten most frequent words of a topic is common in
                most topic modelling papers, it is in fact more insightful to look at the number of words of which the
                sum of probabilities equalizes a certain percentage.
            </p>
            <p>Topic modelling is an unsupervised method, which means that the model makes &#x2018;a wager that patterns
                in the data are sufficiently strong that different latent classes of observations will make themselves
                &#x201C;visible&#x201D;&#x200A;&#x2019;.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">
                    <sup>31</sup>
                </xref>
                This means that the algorithm is not informed about the kind of texts that are imported and what themes
                it has to look for. The algorithm infers information about individual word meanings based on their
                repeated appearance in similar contextual situations.
            </p>
            <p>For the purposes of this study, topic modelling was performed using the Python package gensim, which
                contains a wrapper for <sc>mallet</sc>, a Java topic modelling toolkit. I used the statistical technique
                Latent Dirichlet Allocation (<sc>lda</sc>), which is implemented in <sc>mallet</sc> as well as in other
                software packages.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">
                    <sup>32</sup>
                </xref>
                <sc>lda</sc> is the most commonly used topic modelling method. &#x2018;Latent&#x2019; refers to the
                concept of latent distributions in the model, and &#x2018;Dirichlet&#x2019; is the name of the most
                commonly used prior distribution, named after the German mathematician Johann Dirichlet. It consists of
                a nested multilevel structure, in which the three levels &#x2013; word, document, and corpus &#x2013;
                are distinguished.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">
                    <sup>33</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>Since topic modelling is an unsupervised method for automatically extracting topics from unlabelled data,
                it can give no guarantees on the reliability and interpretability of the output. A method to measure the
                coherence of the topics is therefore highly desirable. A coherent topic is a topic that is semantically
                interpretable: if a topic consists of the words <italic>Jezus</italic>, <italic>kruis</italic> (cross), <italic>
                    lijden
                </italic> (suffering), and <italic>Golgotha</italic>, we are clearly dealing with the crucifixion of
                Christ. However, a topic can also be a result of either the model&#x2019;s design settings, or of
                artefacts in the corpus, such as selection criteria leading to an imbalance in represented genres,
                resulting in topics in which this imbalance is reproduced. This can (but does not necessarily have to)
                result in a topic that is not semantically interpretable. An example would be a topic consisting of the
                words <italic>kribbe</italic> (manger), <italic>prins</italic> (prince), <italic>Holland</italic>, <italic>
                    geus
                </italic> (beggar), <italic>Venus</italic>, and <italic>minne</italic> (love). A coherence measure
                indicates whether the formed topics are indeed semantically interpretable.
            </p>
            <p>In a 2015 study, Michael R&#x00F6;der, Andreas Both, and Alexander Hinneburg evaluated the performance of
                several coherence measures. They concluded that the best performing coherence measure was a rather
                unexplored one, which they labeled
                <italic>C<sub>v</sub>.
                </italic>
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">
                    <sup>34</sup>
                </xref>
                <italic>C
                    <sub>v</sub>
                </italic>
                is based on four parts: i) segmentation of the data into word pairs; ii) calculation of word or
                word-pair probabilities; iii) calculation of a confirmation measure that quantifies how strongly a word
                set supports another word set; and iv) aggregation of individual confirmation measures into an overall
                coherence score.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">
                    <sup>35</sup>
                </xref>
                The coherence score is a value between 0 and 1. In general, a higher coherence score indicates a better
                quality of topic model.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">
                    <sup>36</sup>
                </xref>
                To determine the settings for some parameters that have to be set in building a topic model, I used
                <italic>C</italic>
                <sub>v</sub>
                as coherence score.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">
                    <sup>37</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>In order to build a topic model with gensim, a few preliminary steps have to be taken. An important first
                step is to reduce spelling variation. The early modern period lacked standardised spelling and grammar,
                which meant that (and was proliferated by the fact that) Dutch authors and printers attached little
                value to consistency in spelling, resulting in the coexistence of multiple variants between, and
                sometimes within, texts. Because topic modelling is based on the position of a unique word in a text
                (and thus each unique spelling variant) and its distribution through a corpus, spelling variation
                disturbs the results of the process. Reducing the variation in spelling is therefore a crucial step that
                needs to be taken. For the English language, several tools have been built over the last years to
                convert historical spelling variants into their modern equivalent. For the Dutch language, however, such
                options are limited, and the tools that are available come with both advantages and disadvantages. For
                the purpose of this study, I used the Dutch setup of the <sc>var</sc>iant Detector (<sc>vard</sc>), a
                semi-automatic tool introduced by Alistair Baron and Paul Rayson in 2005.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">
                    <sup>38</sup>
                </xref>
                The tool uses two lists (a normalized word list and a variant list) to suggest or replace variant words
                with their normalized counterparts. The normalization suggestions are given based on a combination of
                four different methods: i) known variant replacements; ii) character edit distance; iii) letter rules;
                and iv) phonetic distance. The Dutch version of <sc>vard</sc>2 was built by Ivan Kisjes and Tessa
                Wijckmans, and was the result of a collaboration between the <sc>create</sc>-project of the University
                of Amsterdam and the Dutch digital research platform <italic>Nederlab</italic>. As a training set, they
                used the first two books of the 1657 edition of the Dutch translation of the Bible.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">
                    <sup>39</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p><sc>vard</sc>2 will find numerous potential normalizations for a given variant. Each of these suggestions
                is given a confidence score, in the form of a percentage expressing how certain the tool is that this is
                the correct normalized word. The suggested normalization with the highest confidence score is used to
                replace each variant. Consider the opening lines of a song from 1598: &#x2018;Reyn maecht
                eerbaer/aenhoort myn claeghen snel&#x2019; (&#x2018;Pure honourable virgin, hear quickly my complaint&#x2019;). <sc>
                    vard</sc>2 suggests normalizations for every word, except the word <italic>snel</italic> (quick).
                The word <italic>reyn</italic> (pure) gets as most popular suggestions the words <italic>rein</italic> (98.47
                percent) and <italic>reen</italic> (0.39 percent). The percentages show that in this case, <italic>
                    rein
                </italic> (clean) is clearly the correct normalization suggestion. For the word <italic>maecht</italic> (virgin),
                however, the tool offers several potential candidates. The words <italic>maagd</italic> (virgin, 95.59
                percent), <italic>macht</italic> (power, 42.71 percent), and <italic>maakt</italic> (makes, 38.52
                percent) are suggested as normalizations, although the high percentage corresponding to <italic>maagd
                </italic> shows that the tool is still confident that this should be the correct normalized word.
            </p>
            <p>However, if the system&#x2019;s normalization methods struggle with a particular variant, the highest
                confidence score may be relatively low &#x2013; in these cases a threshold is required, which is the
                minimum confidence score needed for normalization to take place. If the threshold is not met by the top
                normalization suggestion, the word will not be normalized, and will be left as a variant. The word <italic>
                    claeghen
                </italic> (to complain) from the earlier-cited song gets as suggested variants <italic>clean</italic> (0.96
                percent) and <italic>clan</italic> (0.93 percent). Clearly, <italic>klagen</italic> is not included in
                the normalized word list. If the threshold is higher than one percent, the word &#x2018;claeghen&#x2019;
                will remain unnormalized. A higher threshold will increase precision but reduce recall. After using a
                single text and checking the number of words that were normalized at different thresholds, I decided to
                set the threshold at fifty percent. Before normalization, the corpus consisted of 217,906 distinct
                words; after normalization with <sc>vard</sc>2 the number of unique words in the corpus was reduced by
                23,857, resulting in a corpus with 194,049 distinct words.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">
                    <sup>40</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>The next pre-processing steps included tokenization &#x2013; meaning that each text was converted to a
                list with separate words, or tokens &#x2013; and punctuation removal. Subsequently, stop words, which
                are the very common words (in this case mostly function words such as personal pronouns, propositions,
                and conjunctions), were removed from the corpus. Using the Python package nltk, a list of one hundred
                and fifty most frequent words was made. Content words were manually removed from this list and therefore
                kept in the corpus.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">
                    <sup>41</sup>
                </xref>
                Furthermore, a threshold was set for words that appear too infrequently in the corpus (no_below).
                Calculating the coherence score of topic models with different settings for no_below, this threshold was
                set at 2, which means that words that appear in only one document are ignored.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">
                    <sup>42</sup>
                </xref>
                The third step was deciding how many topics the model would be creating. Here the coherence score was
                used again. I built ten topic models with different values for the number of topics, in the range
                10:100. The coherence score of each model was calculated. It turned out that the model with fifty topics
                obtained the highest coherence score, and therefore I decided to build the final topic model using this
                setting.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">
                    <sup>43</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>The output of a topic model consists of two dataframes (tables): one with the keys of a topic model, the
                other one with the composition. The dataframe &#x2018;keys&#x2019; contains fifty rows, one for each
                topic, and two columns: one for the topic id, the other for the words that form a specific topic. The
                dataframe &#x2018;composition&#x2019; contains as many rows as there are documents in the corpus. The
                columns are numbered from 0 to 49, corresponding with the id of the topics from &#x2018;keys&#x2019;.
                The cells from each row contain a value between 0 and 1. The higher a value, the more dominant that
                topic is in a document. Note that the sum of each row will always be 1, but that the distribution always
                differs.
            </p>
            <p>After building the final topic model, another tool was used to measure the quality of the model, and to
                get more insight into the topics and how they are related to each other. I used the Python package
                py<sc>lda</sc>vis, which is a library for interactive topic model visualization. The package extracts
                information from a fitted <sc>lda</sc> topic model to inform an interactive web-based visualization.
                After a few steps of pre-processing, the output is an Intertopic Distance Map. <xref ref-type="fig"
                                                                                                     rid="fg003">Fig. 3
                </xref> gives an example of the data visualized, in this case topic 27 (&#x2018;world &#x0026; money&#x2019;).
                Each bubble on the left-hand side of the plot represents a topic.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">
                    <sup>44</sup>
                </xref>
                The larger the bubble, the more prevalent the topic is within the corpus. A good topic model should have
                bubbles scattered throughout the chart, rather than clustered in a single quadrant. A model with too
                many topics will typically have many overlapping small-sized bubbles clustered in one region of the
                chart. When hovering over the topics, the thirty most prevalent words of that topic are visualized on
                the right-hand side. Since a topic model only produces bags of words as output, users have to manually
                interpret the words that make up a topic. To do so, I looked at the number of words that together made
                up fifteen percent of a given topic. I built a word cloud from every topic, visualizing the upper
                fifteen percent of words and their weights within a topic. The top thirty words and their weights within
                every topic are included in an online appendix.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">
                    <sup>45</sup>
                </xref>
                The topics and the subjects I assigned to them can be found in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tb002">tab.
                    2</xref>.
            </p>
            <table-wrap id="tb002">
                <label>Tab. 2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Dominant topics in the Dutch Song Database by sum of weights (&#x003E;&#x003D; 0.1).</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Topic no.</th>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Subject</th>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Sum of weights (&#x003E; 0.1)</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">9</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion &#x0026; old spelling</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">2847</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">31</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1684</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">0</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion &#x0026; life</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1508</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">18</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1357</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">19</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">verbs</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1312</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">39</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">love &#x0026; sadness</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1172</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">13</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1096</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">38</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">love &#x0026; happiness</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1072</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">28</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">prayer &#x0026; preaching</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1026</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">24</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">rejection</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">997</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">10</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">suffering &#x0026; sadness</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">799</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">love &#x0026; tragedy</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">788</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">6</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">possessives</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">782</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">36</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">776</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion &#x0026; Mary</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">776</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">3</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">verbs</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">769</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">30</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">love</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">761</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">48</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">love</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">739</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">27</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">world &#x0026; money</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">738</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">5</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">christmas</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">735</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">God &#x0026; enemy</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">715</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">49</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">God &#x0026; country (praise)</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">691</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">32</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">nation &#x0026; country</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">670</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">46</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">life &#x0026; sin</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">642</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">12</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">marriage</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">635</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">8</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">life &#x0026; praise</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">631</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">44</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion &#x0026; virtue</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">624</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">15</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Old Testament</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">614</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">47</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">bucolic</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">613</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">21</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">love &#x0026; happiness</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">591</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">42</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Good Friday &#x0026; Easter</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">571</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">16</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">good &#x0026; evil</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">567</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">14</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">myth &#x0026; beauty</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">559</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">23</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">physical love</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">533</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">40</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">New Testament</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">529</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">17</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">heaven &#x0026; happiness</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">524</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion &#x0026; happiness</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">509</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">34</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">seduction</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">479</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">29</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">drinking</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">465</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">37</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">nature</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">433</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">11</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">unclear</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">345</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">26</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">money &#x0026; work</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">307</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">33</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">unclear</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">285</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">35</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">religion</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">264</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">45</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">old or odd spelling</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">259</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">25</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">sea</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">248</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">22</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">church</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">203</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">41</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">German</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">171</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">43</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">French</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">119</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">20</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">solfege</td>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">92</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>Source: Dutch Song Database.</p>
                </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <fig id="fg003" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 3</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Visualization of topic 27 (&#x2018;world &#x0026; money&#x2019;) in the Dutch Song Database,
                        1550-1750, using py<sc>lda</sc>vis.
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig3.jpg"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4">
            <title>Dominant Topics</title>
            <p>The appendix also includes a column with the sum of the weights of the top thirty words. The lower this
                value, the &#x2018;flatter&#x2019; the distribution of words within a topic, suggesting that the words
                in these topics are not typical for that specific topic, but occur in many other topics as well. The
                clearest example of such a word is &#x2018;God&#x2019;: this word has the highest weight in ten topics.
                Still, its probability can be fairly low (0.00992 in topic 7, 0.0131 in topic 28). An example of a topic
                with a high sum of weights of the first thirty words is topic 29 (0.2493), to which I assigned the label
                &#x2018;drinking&#x2019;, due to words such as <italic>wijn</italic> (wine), <italic>drinken</italic> (to
                drink), <italic>vrolijk</italic> (merry), drinkt (drinks), and <italic>bier</italic> (beer). Another
                clear example is topic 46 (0.2620), to which &#x2018;life &#x0026; sin&#x2019; was assigned, because of
                the presence of words such as <italic>wereld</italic> (world), <italic>God</italic>, <italic>leven
                </italic> (life), <italic>kwaad</italic> (evil), and <italic>sterven</italic> (to die). Topic 5 was
                labelled as &#x2018;Christmas&#x2019;, due to words as <italic>kindeken</italic> (baby), <italic>stal
                </italic> (stable), <italic>Bethlehem</italic>, and <italic>Maria</italic>. I assigned &#x2018;love
                &#x0026; sadness&#x2019; to topic 39, because of the presence of positive words such as <italic>lief
                </italic> (sweetheart), <italic>liefde</italic> (love), <italic>min</italic> (love), and <italic>
                    schone
                </italic> (beautiful) on the one hand, and negative words such as <italic>ach</italic> (oh!), <italic>
                    pijn
                </italic> (hurt), <italic>smart</italic> (grief), and <italic>verdriet</italic> (sorrow) on the other.
                This topic differs from another topic on love (topic 38) in that almost all the words in this topic are
                positive: <italic>hart</italic> (heart), <italic>vreugd</italic> (joy), <italic>leven</italic> (life), <italic>
                    min
                </italic> (love), and <italic>vermaak</italic> (entertainment). I assigned &#x2018;love &#x0026;
                happiness&#x2019; to this topic.
            </p>
            <p>I labelled topic 32 &#x2018;nation &#x0026; country&#x2019;: the words <italic>prins</italic> (prince), <italic>
                stad
            </italic> (city), <italic>land</italic> (country), <italic>graaf</italic> (count), and <italic>Holland
            </italic> leave no doubt that these are words from political songs. However, the sum of weights of the first
                thirty words in this topic is rather low: 0.1342. The same goes for topic 14. While the words all refer
                to a topic that I labelled &#x2018;myth &#x0026; beauty&#x2019; (including <italic>Venus</italic>, <italic>
                    schoonheid
                </italic> (beauty), <italic>gezicht</italic> (face), <italic>glans</italic> (shine), and <italic>goden
                </italic> (gods)), the sum of weights is only 0.1429. This suggests that these topics have a flat
                distribution. In topic 47, words from pastoral or bucolic songs are clustered. Many words refer to the
                shepherd&#x2019;s life, such as <italic>vee</italic> (cattle), <italic>herder</italic> (shepherd), <italic>
                    bos
                </italic> (forest), and <italic>schaepjes</italic> (little sheep). I assigned the label &#x2018;bucolic&#x2019;
                to this topic. Topic 28 was labelled &#x2018;prayer &#x0026; preaching&#x2019;, because apart from the
                obvious religious words, there are words in this topic that have an oral connotation &#x2013; <italic>
                    hoort
                </italic> (hears), <italic>horen</italic> (to hear), <italic>zeid</italic> (said), <italic>verstaat
                </italic> (understands), <italic>vermaan</italic> (admonish), and <italic>broeders</italic> (brothers).
                It turns out that many topics have something to do with religion. This is not surprising, since we
                already know that almost forty percent of the corpus are songs from the category &#x2018;religion&#x2019;.
                In some cases, it is quite easy to define a label for a topic (such as &#x2018;religion &#x0026;
                happiness&#x2019;, &#x2018;religion &#x0026; sin&#x2019;), but in other cases the differences are more
                difficult to distinguish.
            </p>
            <p>To examine which topics dominate the corpus, I selected for each song the topics that covered at least
                ten percent of the song, meaning that a topic has a minimal weight of 0.1 in a song. Subsequently, I
                summed these weights per topic (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tb002">tab. 2</xref>). The topics are
                ranked by the sum of their weights. Topic 9 is by far the most popular within the corpus. The appendix
                shows this topic has a rather &#x2018;flat&#x2019; probability distribution: the five most frequent
                words in this topic (<italic>god</italic>, <italic>wt</italic>, <italic>leun</italic>, <italic>
                    gods</italic>, <italic>nv</italic>) all have a weight of between 0.01 and 0.02. The oddly spelled
                words such as <italic>wt</italic>, <italic>leun</italic>, <italic>nv</italic>, <italic>
                    si</italic>, <italic>bouen</italic>, and <italic>ouer</italic> suggest that topic 9 is rather a
                result of artefacts in the corpus: the tool used for spelling normalization does not work well on texts
                written before 1637. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg004">Fig. 4</xref> confirms this hypothesis: topic 9
                peaks between 1550 and 1600, but descends soon after.
            </p>
            <fig id="fg004" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 4</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Relative frequency of topic 9 in the Dutch Song Database, by annual sum of weights (&#x003E;&#x003D;
                        0.1).
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig4.jpg"/>
            </fig>
            <p>The rest of the top ten of most dominant topics is made up by topics that relate either to religion or to
                love, except topic 19, in which words are not clustered on semantic similarity, but on linguistic
                characteristics. I labelled this topic as &#x2018;verbs&#x2019;, because it consists of words such as <italic>
                    leven
                </italic> (to live), <italic>zullen</italic> (shall), <italic>geven</italic> (to give), and <italic>
                    komen
                </italic> (to come). The relatively low sum of weights of the first thirty words (0.1573) indicates that
                these words are not very distinctive for this particular topic, but occur in many other topics. If we
                take a look at the bottom of the chart, the opposite is the case. Topic 41 consists of German words (<italic>
                    das
                </italic> (the), <italic>mein</italic> (mine), <italic>mir</italic> (to me), <italic>ein</italic> (a/an), <italic>
                    mit
                </italic> (with)) and has a sum of weights that is above average (0.2697). The same goes for topic 43,
                which consists of French words and has a sum of weights of 0.3463, as well as for topic 20, consisting
                of interjections that often occur in children&#x2019;s or folklore songs, with a sum of weights of
                0.5108. These high values indicate that these words are rather distinctive for these topics.
            </p>
            <p>The most dominant topics in the corpus, then, are &#x2018;religion plus something&#x2019;. This is not a
                surprising result, because the distribution of categories already indicated many religious topics.
                Still, the topic model has uncovered many differences within the wide-ranging genres of songs. Although
                many more observations can be made with regard to the fifty most distinctive topics, the next two
                sections will explore how the dominance of song topics fluctuates in the context of the two cases I
                introduced earlier: Petrarchan songs and patriotic songs. As we have seen, these are topics that are
                popular within the corpus, and based on qualitative research we would expect to see some changes over
                time regarding their popularity. A quantitative approach can be used to detect this.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s5">
            <title>Petrarchism Songs</title>
            <p>Based on the existing literature, song topics related to the Petrarchistic tradition should be peaking in
                the beginning of the seventeenth century. These could be topics on the tragic aspects of love, but also
                topics which can be related to the Renaissance and classical tradition, for example the bucolic genre.
                Two dominant topics in the second-largest overarching category &#x2013; love &#x2013; are contradictory:
                topic 39, &#x2018;love &#x0026; sadness&#x2019;, and topic 38, &#x2018;love &#x0026; happiness&#x2019;. <xref
                        ref-type="fig" rid="fg005">Fig. 5
                </xref> shows the evolution of these two topics over time, which reveals an interesting pattern: for
                instance, the topic &#x2018;love &#x0026; sadness&#x2019; peaks about fifty years before the topic
                &#x2018;love &#x0026; happiness&#x2019;.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">
                    <sup>46</sup>
                </xref>
                Initially, topic 39 is dominant, but by 1700, topic 38 (&#x2018;love &#x0026; happiness&#x2019;) picks
                up and rapidly becomes the dominant of the two love topics. The topic &#x2018;love &#x0026; sadness&#x2019;
                does increase slightly in the eighteenth century, but never comes close to &#x2018;love &#x0026;
                happiness&#x2019;. &#x2018;Love &#x0026; sadness&#x2019; can be seen as a typical Petrarchan topic: the
                words <italic>ach</italic> (woe!) and <italic>pijn</italic> (pain) in this topic speak for themselves. <xref
                        ref-type="fig" rid="fg005">Fig. 5
                </xref> demonstrates that the popularity of these songs peaked in the early seventeenth century, as
                expected. It also suggests that towards the end of the seventeenth century, songs with negative emotions
                were replaced by songs with a rosier view on love.
            </p>
            <fig id="fg005" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 5</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Relative frequency of topics 38 and 39 in the Dutch Song Database, by annual sum of weights (&#x003E;&#x003D;
                        0.1).
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig5.jpg"/>
            </fig>
            <p>
                <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg006">Fig. 6</xref>
                shows additional love topics besides the two discussed above, demonstrating that another Petrarchan
                topic (2, &#x2018;love &#x0026; tragedy&#x2019;) had in fact peaked in the first quarter of the
                seventeenth century, before being replaced by topic 39. When we take a closer look at the words that
                form the latter two topics, it becomes clear that they exhibit many similarities: both contain the words <italic>
                liefste
            </italic> (dearest), <italic>liefde</italic> (love), <italic>herte</italic> (heart), <italic>minnen</italic> (to
                love), <italic>pijn</italic> (pain), and <italic>verdriet</italic> (sorrow). However, both topics also
                contain distinctly different words: topic 2 includes words such as <italic>troost</italic> (consolation), <italic>
                lijden
            </italic> (suffering), <italic>genezen</italic> (to heal), and <italic>scheiden</italic> (to separate),
                while topic 39 consists of words such as <italic>smert</italic> (grief), <italic>waarom</italic> (why), <italic>
                droeve
            </italic> (sad), and <italic>sterven</italic> (to die). Semantically the topics are related, but they
                include different words. Taken together, the two topics suggest the dominance of tragic love over all
                other love tropes in songs published between 1575 and 1685.
            </p>
            <fig id="fg006" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 6</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Relative frequency of topics 2, 23, 24, 34, 38, and 39 in the Dutch Song Database, by annual sum
                        of weights (&#x003E;&#x003D; 0.1).
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig6.jpg"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Topic 24 (&#x2018;rejection&#x2019;) peaked simultaneously with &#x2018;love &#x0026; sadness&#x2019;,
                between 1650 and 1675. Other love variants, such as &#x2018;seduction&#x2019; and &#x2018;physical love&#x2019;,
                are less prevalent, but still peak at the same time as topics 39 and 24. These topics may also be
                connected to the heyday of Petrarchism. A famous Dutch imitator of Petrarch was Pieter Corneliszoon
                Hooft, whose poems were largely based on the Petrarchan exemplar, in particular the conventions of
                amorous lyric. The case of Hooft demonstrates that not only poems but also songs were written with the
                Petrarchan tradition in mind. Hooft&#x2019;s songs ended up in songbooks, accompanied by melodies, and
                reached a large audience. From 1607, song poets often referred when assigning their melodies to songs
                from Hooft&#x2019;s play <italic>Granida</italic> (1605).
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">
                    <sup>47</sup>
                </xref>
                These observations are reflected in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg006">fig. 6</xref>, which shows that
                various love topics, which in their own way all relate to Petrarchan love poetry, dominated between 1575
                and 1650.
            </p>
            <p>Other topics related to the humanistic tradition are &#x2018;bucolic&#x2019;, &#x2018;myth &#x0026;
                beauty&#x2019;, and &#x2018;nature&#x2019;, which are visualized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg007">
                    fig. 7</xref>. &#x2018;Bucolic&#x2019; refers to the pastoral, a genre originating in the classical
                tradition and especially in the works of Theocritus and Virgil. The use of mythological figures such as
                Venus and Phoebus in topic 14 also indicates the imitation of classical genres. There is a clear decline
                in these topics after 1660. &#x2018;Love &#x0026; sadness&#x2019;, &#x2018;love &#x0026; tragedy&#x2019;,
                and &#x2018;rejection&#x2019; are overtaken by &#x2018;love &#x0026; happiness&#x2019; (<xref
                        ref-type="fig" rid="fg006">fig. 6</xref>). The Petrarchan tradition with negative emotions on
                love seems to have moved to the background, making room for a less dramatic, more light-hearted
                interpretation of love. An explanation could be that the moralistic attitude described by Keersmaekers,
                which can be linked to the culture of piety that was blooming in the seventeenth century, was beginning
                to diminish. Qualitative research could provide more insight into whether (and if so, why) the depiction
                of the Petrarchan tradition in songs declined in the course of the eighteenth century.
            </p>
            <fig id="fg007" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 7</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Relative frequency of topics 14, 37, and 47 in the Dutch Song Database, by annual sum of weights
                        (&#x003E;&#x003D; 0.1).
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig7.jpg"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s6">
            <title>Patriotic Identity</title>
            <p>Scholarship has suggested that topics dealing with nation and country peaked during the Dutch Revolt,
                although they remained dominant after the 1648 Peace of M&#x00FC;nster. I have selected three topics
                related to politics to test this hypothesis. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg008">Fig. 8</xref> shows that
                topic 32 (&#x2018;nation and country&#x2019;) appeared around 1575 and steadily rose thereafter. The
                topic remained dominant for at least fifty-five years, a timespan largely coinciding with the Dutch
                Revolt. Dominant words in this topic are <italic>prins</italic> (prince), <italic>land</italic> (country), <italic>
                    graaf
                </italic> (count), <italic>spaensche</italic> (Spanish), and <italic>paus</italic> (pope), confirming
                that these topics are indeed covered by the beggar songs, which were extremely popular during the Dutch
                Revolt. It seems likely that the many reprints of the <italic>Nieu Geusen liedtboecxken</italic> (published
                between 1577 and 1687) are responsible for the dominance of this topic. The song that is most emblematic
                for topic 32 (because of its high weight) is titled &#x2018;Wel op wel op Spangiaerden&#x2019;, an
                anti-Spanish song from the <italic>Nieu Geusen liedtboecxken</italic>.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">
                    <sup>48</sup>
                </xref>
                However, more songbooks with patriotic songs existed in the Dutch Republic.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">
                    <sup>49</sup>
                </xref>
                Although some of the songs in these songbooks were also included in the beggar songbooks, others that
                would have fitted the criteria were not. Topic 32 shows a drastic fall around 1640, which coincides with
                the Peace of M&#x00FC;nster in 1648. The topic is no longer dominant in subsequent decades, bar a little
                revival between 1675 and 1725. Since all graphs use a rolling average over twenty years, this revival
                could be the result of the last reprint of the <italic>Nieu Geusen liedtboecxken</italic> in 1687. All
                in all, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg008">fig. 8</xref> suggests that the dominance shown by this topic
                during the Dutch Revolt did not return, merely that there is perhaps a renewed popularity of patriotic
                songs during the War of the Spanish Succession (1701-1714), though the line&#x2019;s erratic course
                demands that caution be shown in making such an interpretation.
            </p>
            <fig id="fg008" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 8</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Relative frequency of topics 7, 32, and 49 in the Dutch Song Database, by annual sum of weights (&#x003E;&#x003D;
                        0.1).
                    </p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="figures/emlc.10908_fig8.jpg"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Around 1625, when topic 32 began to decrease, the two others gained in popularity, of which &#x2018;God
                and enemy&#x2019; became even more dominant than topic 32. An important contrast between topics 7 and 49
                on the one hand, and topic 32 on the other, is the presence of religious words in topics 7 and 49. The
                only religious word in topic 32 is <italic>God</italic>, with a considerably lower weight, given that
                words such as <italic>prins</italic> (prince), <italic>land</italic> (country), <italic>stad</italic> (city),
                and <italic>vijand</italic> (enemy) are more prevalent. Topics 7 and 49 contain more overlap with other
                religious topics, with the presence of such words as <italic>God</italic>, <italic>boze</italic> (angry), <italic>
                    Gods
                </italic> (God&#x2019;s), and <italic>handen</italic> (hands) in topic 7, and <italic>God</italic>, <italic>
                    zijne
                </italic> (His), <italic>naam</italic> (name), <italic>heren</italic> (the Lord&#x2019;s), and <italic>
                    hemel
                </italic> (heaven) in topic 49. This suggests these are religious songs with a strong focus on the
                aspects of war, peace, enemy, and the people. The song with the highest weight contribution to topic 49
                turns out to be a psalm in a translation by Petrus Datheen; indeed, many other songs with a high weight
                contribution to topic 49 are also psalms. This is not surprising, as many psalms use a vocabulary that
                expresses a battle against a real or imaginary enemy. The song with the highest weight contribution to
                topic 7 is from the songbook <italic>Stichtelijcke Gesangen</italic> (1661) and relates the story of the
                biblical figure Daniel, who was thrown into a lion&#x2019;s den:
            </p>
            <disp-quote>
                <p>When Daniel came in the den</p>
                <p>Of cruel lions</p>
                <p>(Who howled with a loud</p>
                <p>Cry of ferocity),</p>
                <p>As if into the abyss,</p>
                <p>Surrounded by wailing,</p>
                <p>The angel, by God&#x2019;s command,</p>
                <p>Held the lions&#x2019; jaws,</p>
                <p>So that they sat meek</p>
                <p>As if they were lambs.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
                <p>The entire world is crawling</p>
                <p>With cruel enemies,</p>
                <p>Who would have defiled us,</p>
                <p>If God had not,</p>
                <p>By his great might,</p>
                <p>Chained their hands:</p>
                <p>But now he puts a limit</p>
                <p>To all the tyrant&#x2019;s work:</p>
                <p>And takes heed of his children,</p>
                <p>Strong and all-knowing.
                    <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">
                        <sup>50</sup>
                    </xref>
                </p>
            </disp-quote>
            <p>Although the first verse relates Daniel&#x2019;s well-known fate, the second contains a reference to a
                war the singer was involved in. This not only ties in with the aforementioned increase in attention paid
                by orthodox ministers to patriotic ideas, but also with a broader trend in orthodox circles: during the
                Further Reformation (a Pietistic movement that began in the second half of the seventeenth century),
                songs were increasingly considered to be a literary genre through which the dissemination of Pietistic
                ideas could take place. Proponents of the Further Reformation published their own catechisms, sermon
                collections, and songbooks, which caused an exponential rise in the number of Reformed songbooks after
                1650.
                <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">
                    <sup>51</sup>
                </xref>
            </p>
            <p>Another explanation for these trends could be that these topics, in addition to their political
                connotation, also have a military meaning. Furthermore, the topics might also be (partly) formed of
                songs in which earlier military events are historicized. In summary, the topics related to the
                fatherland not only show how these songs prevailed during political conflict, but the patriotic ideas
                they embodied also became increasingly embedded in the seventeenth-century Pietistic tradition.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s7">
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            <p>This article has shown that computational methods for text analysis offer a meaningful way to analyse a
                large digital corpus. The benefits of this study are, therefore, multiple: first and foremost, topic
                modelling has provided a possible solution to the issues addressed in the introduction &#x2013; the lack
                of metadata on genres in the Dutch Song Database, and the impossibility of searching for genre patterns
                in this collection. Although the dominance of religious and love topics was to be expected, given the
                existing genre classification of the database, this study shows that subcategories can be defined within
                a genre. For example, the built topic model was able to distinguish between several aspects of love,
                different focuses within the topic &#x2018;religion&#x2019;, and differences in songs with political
                connotations. These results contribute to a better understanding of the richness of the Dutch Song
                Database. A recommended next step would be to supplement the missing metadata on genres in the database
                with the results from this study, as this would facilitate its use by other researchers.
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by exploring the relationship between topical fluctuations and cultural-historical changes in
                the Dutch Republic, I have shown how quantitatively obtained results can be related to existing
                scholarship on early modern Dutch song culture. This study confirms that Petrarchan ideas were indeed
                transmitted through song, a phenomenon that began in the early seventeenth century. Furthermore, the
                results suggest that the Petrarchan tradition in songs started to decline in the course of the
                eighteenth century. In addition, this study shows that songs with a patriotic identity became more
                popular during political crises, and that songs belonging to the religious genre were also used to
                spread patriotic ideas, a trend coinciding with the heyday of the Further Reformation.
            </p>
            <p>More generally, I have shown how, with the methodology used in this study, diachronic developments in
                textual corpora can be explored. This particular study shows how song lyrics interfere with and react to
                socio-cultural and political developments, thus demonstrating that songs are a suitable medium through
                which the historian may gauge the social climate. The question rises, however, whether songs are
                precursors to or merely the result of socio-cultural trends, something that deserves further research.
                Furthermore, the proposed method should be improved, so that it may be applied to other corpora, both
                early modern and modern, both in Dutch and other languages.
            </p>
            <p>A few remarks should be made regarding the methods used and the results obtained. In the first place,
                this study shows the complexity of using historical textual data on a large scale. Although retaining
                spelling variation might be necessary for other studies or disciplines, in this case it was important
                that spelling be normalized across the corpus. The method used to reduce spelling variation in this
                study is not flawless. For example, because the training set of the tool was built from
                seventeenth-century material, contemporary words were not normalized by the tool. This resulted in
                topics that were not semantically interpretable; rather, a group of word clusters formed that were based
                purely on the fact that their words were not normalized. Clear examples are topics 9 and 45, which
                contain words such as <italic>dij</italic>, <italic>yn</italic>, <italic>soe</italic>, <italic>
                    uwz</italic>, <italic>jon</italic>, and <italic>fen</italic>. This shows once again that more
                research into techniques to deal with historical variation in Dutch spelling is crucial.
            </p>
            <p>It must also be noted that topic modelling is an oft-debated computational method, not only because it is
                based on probabilities and the mathematical idea behind the method seems a mystery to many users, but
                also because it is clear that more work is required on measures to evaluate the results. In this study,
                evaluation was done by using coherence measures and visualizations, but it is important to stress that
                these evaluation methods are also not flawless. Another point where intervention of the researcher may
                have led to biased results was the assigning of a description to topics. This was done by looking at the
                word cloud of a topic&#x2019;s fifteen percent most dominant words, but it is entirely possible that
                another researcher would have assigned different subjects to the topics.
            </p>
            <p>In general, it should be noted that when using topic modelling, songs originating from a certain context,
                and sung by multiple groups of peoples for various reasons, are simply reduced to groups of words. It is
                always necessary, therefore, to interpret and evaluate the results of a topic model in detail, as well
                as put them in the cultural, sociological, and historical context in which the texts were produced. I
                have tried to do this to a certain extent, but further research can undoubtedly improve my findings. The
                same goes for other aspects of songs and song cultures that were not taken into account in this study,
                but that can certainly affect a song&#x2019;s popularity, such as its musical style and communal singing
                practices.
            </p>
            <p>Scholars have published many qualitative studies on well-known and lesser-known songs, songbooks, and
                song writers from the Dutch Republic. The aim of this study, in contrast, has been to offer a
                quantitative perspective, and to demonstrate how the combination of both approaches can offer new
                perspectives to the field of early modern literary studies. My quantitative research has generated new
                hypotheses about the Dutch song culture that merit investigation, both by quantitative <italic>and
                </italic> qualitative literary researchers and cultural historians. I believe that zooming out, while
                inevitably rendering some details invisible, allows us to see new patterns and generate new hypotheses
                that can improve our understanding of not only early modern song culture, but Dutch culture at large.
            </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>Bibliography</title>
            <ref id="r1">
                <mixed-citation>Blei, David M., Andrew Y. Ng, Michael I. Jordan, and John Lafferty (eds.), &#x2018;Latent
                    Dirichlet Allocation&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Machine Learning Research</italic> 3 (2003/4-5)
                    993-1022.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r2">
                <mixed-citation>Bork, Gerrit Jan van, et al., <italic>Algemeen Letterkundig Lexicon</italic> (Leiden
                    2012).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r3">
                <mixed-citation>Bruin, Martine de, &#x2018;Het Wilhelmus tijdens de Republiek&#x2019;, in Louis Peter
                    Grijp (ed.), <italic>Nationale hymnen. Het Wilhelmus en zijn buren</italic> (Amsterdam 1998) 16-42.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r4">
                <mixed-citation>
                    <italic>Een Nieu Geuse Lieden boecxken</italic>
                    (Enkhuizen: Jan Jacobs Palensteyn, 1625).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r5">
                <mixed-citation>Egghe, Leo, and Goran Proot, &#x2018;The Estimation of the Number of Lost Multi-Copy
                    Documents. A New Type of Informetrics Theory&#x2019;, <italic>Journal of Informetrics</italic> 1
                    (2007/4) 257-268.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r6">
                <mixed-citation>Gelderblom, Arie-Jan, &#x2018;Investing in Your Relationship&#x2019;, in Els Stronks and
                    Peter Boot (eds.), <italic>Learned Love. Proceedings of the Emblem Project Utrecht Conference on
                        Dutch Love Emblems and the Internet
                    </italic> (The Hague 2007) 131-142.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r7">
                <mixed-citation>Grijp, Louis Peter, <italic>Het Nederlandse lied in de Gouden Eeuw. Het mechanisme van
                    de contrafactuur
                </italic> (Amsterdam 1991).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r8">
                <mixed-citation>Grootes, Eddy, &#x2018;Het jeugdig publiek van de &#x201C;nieuwe liedboeken&#x201D; in
                    het eerste kwart van de zeventiende eeuw&#x2019;, in Willem van den Berg and Hanna Stouten (eds.), <italic>
                        Het woord aan de lezer. Zeven literatuurhistorische verkenningen
                    </italic> (Groningen 1987) 72-88.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r9">
                <mixed-citation>Grootes, Eddy, &#x2018;Liedjes over de Tachtigjarige Oorlog in andere bundels dan het
                    Geuzenliedboek&#x2019;, <italic>De Zeventiende Eeuw</italic> 13 (1997/1) 173-179.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r10">
                <mixed-citation>Hooft, Pieter Cornelisz, <italic>Granida</italic>. Lia van Gemert (ed.) (Amsterdam
                    1998).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r11">
                <mixed-citation>Jensen, Lotte (ed.), <italic>The Roots of Nationalism. National Identity Formation in
                    Early Modern Europe, 1600-1815
                </italic> (Amsterdam 2016).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r12">
                <mixed-citation>Karsdorp, Folgert, Mike Kestemont, and Allen Riddell, <italic>Humanities Data Analysis.
                    Case Studies with Python
                </italic> (Princeton 2021).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r13">
                <mixed-citation>Keersmaekers, August Albert, <italic>Wandelend in Den Nieuwen Lust-Hof. Studie over een
                    Amsterdams liedboek 1602-(1604)-1607-(1610)
                </italic> (Nijmegen 1985).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r14">
                <mixed-citation>Kestemont, Mike, and Folgert Karsdorp, &#x2018;Estimating the Loss of Medieval
                    Literature with an Unseen Species Model from Ecodiversity&#x2019;, <italic>Proceedings of the
                        Workshop on Computational Humanities Research (CHR 2020)
                    </italic> (Amsterdam 2020) 44-55.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r15">
                <mixed-citation>Kestemont, Mike, et al., <italic>Van wie is het Wilhelmus? De auteur van het Nederlandse
                    volkslied met de computer onderzocht
                </italic> (Amsterdam 2017).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r16">
                <mixed-citation>Kisjes, Ivan, and Tessa Wijckmans, &#x2018;Adapting a Spelling Normalization Tool
                    Designed for English to 17th Century Dutch&#x2019;, <italic>Proceedings of the Digital Humanities
                        Conference 2018
                    </italic> (Mexico City 2018) 412-413.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r17">
                <mixed-citation>Kranenburg, Peter van, Martine de Bruin, and Anja Volk, &#x2018;Documenting a Song
                    Culture. The Dutch Song Database as a Resource for Musicological Research&#x2019;, <italic>
                        International Journal on Digital Libraries
                    </italic> 20 (2019/1) 13-23.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r18">
                <mixed-citation>Maertsz., Cornelis, <italic>Stichtelijcke Gesangen, behelsende Bybelsche In-vallen,
                    Geestelijcke Bedenckingen, Eerlycke Vermaeckingen
                </italic> (Hoorn: Gerbrant and Jan Martensz., 1661).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r19">
                <mixed-citation>Poel, Dieuwke van der, Louis Peter Grijp, and Wim van Anrooij (eds.), <italic>Identity,
                    Intertextuality, and Performance in Early Modern Song Culture
                </italic> (Leiden 2016).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r20">
                <mixed-citation>Porteman, K., et al., <italic>Een nieuw vaderland voor de muzen. Geschiedenis van de
                    Nederlandse literatuur 1560-1700
                </italic> (Amsterdam 2009).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r21">
                <mixed-citation>Pritchard, Jonathan K., Matthew Stephens, and Peter Donnelly, &#x2018;Inference of
                    population structure using multilocus genotype data&#x2019;, <italic>Genetics</italic> 155 (2000/2)
                    945-959.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r22">
                <mixed-citation>Proot, Goran, &#x2018;Survival Factors of Seventeenth-Century Hand-Press Books Published
                    in the Southern Netherlands. The Importance of Sheet Counts, Sammelb&#x00E4;nde and the Role of
                    Institutional Collections&#x2019;, in Andrew Pettegree and Flavia Bruni (eds.), <italic>Lost Books.
                        Reconstructing the Print World of Pre-Industrial Europe
                    </italic> (Leiden 2016) 160-201.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r23">
                <mixed-citation>Proot, Goran, and Leo Egghe, &#x2018;Estimating Editions on the Basis of Survivals.
                    Printed Programmes of Jesuit Plays in the &#x201C;Provincia Flandro-Belgica&#x201D; before 1773,
                    with a Note on the &#x201C;Book Historical Law&#x201D;&#x2019;, <italic>The Papers of the
                        Bibliographical Society of America
                    </italic> 102 (2008/2) 149-174.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r24">
                <mixed-citation>R&#x00F6;der, Michael, Andreas Both, and Alexander Hinneburg, &#x2018;Exploring the
                    Space of Topic Coherence Measures&#x2019;, <italic>Proceedings of the Eighth ACM International
                        Conference on Web Search and Data Mining &#x2013; WSDM&#x2019; 15
                    </italic> (Shanghai 2015) 399-408.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r25">
                <mixed-citation>Stronks, Els, &#x2018;Identiteiten van adolescenten in de vroegmoderne liedcultuur. Het
                    studentenlied als casus&#x2019;, <italic>Nederlandse Letterkunde</italic> 17 (2012/3) 225-248.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r26">
                <mixed-citation>Stronks, Els, &#x2018;&#x201C;Dees kennisse zuldy te kope vinnen&#x201D;. Liedcultuur en
                    de waarde van &#x201C;know how&#x201D; in de vroegmoderne Republiek&#x2019;, <italic>De Zeventiende
                        Eeuw
                    </italic> 30 (2014/2) 147-167.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r27">
                <mixed-citation>Syed, Shaheen, and Marco Spruit, &#x2018;Full-Text or Abstract? Examining Topic
                    Coherence Scores Using Latent Dirichlet Allocation&#x2019;, <italic>2017 IEEE International
                        Conference on Data Science and Advanced Analytics (DSAA)
                    </italic> (Tokyo 2017) 165-174.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r28">
                <mixed-citation>Uglanova, Inna, and Evelyn Gius, &#x2018;The Order of Things. A Study on Topic Modelling
                    of Literary Texts&#x2019;, <italic>Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Humanities Research
                        (CHR 2020)
                    </italic> (Amsterdam 2020) 57-76.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r29">
                <mixed-citation>Van der Haven, Cornelis, &#x2018;Patriotism and Bellicism in German and Dutch Epics of
                    the Enlightenment&#x2019;, <italic>Arcadia</italic> 47 (2012/1) 54-77.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r30">
                <mixed-citation>Veldhorst, Natascha, &#x2018;Pharmacy for the Body and Soul. Dutch Songbooks in the
                    Seventeenth Century&#x2019;, <italic>Early Music History</italic> 27 (2008) 217-285.
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r31">
                <mixed-citation>Veldhorst, Natascha, <italic>Zingend door het leven. Het Nederlandse liedboek in de
                    Gouden Eeuw
                </italic> (Amsterdam 2009).
                </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
                <label>1</label>
                <p>Grijp, <italic>Het Nederlandse lied</italic>, 29. This article is based on the thesis I wrote to
                    complete the research master&#x2019;s degree in Dutch literature and culture at Utrecht University
                    in July 2019, supervised by Els Stronks and Folgert Karsdorp. I would like to thank Joris Veerbeek
                    for being my Python lifeline, and Lucas van der Deijl, Milan van Lange, Judith Pollmann, Kim Smeenk,
                    the editorial board of
                    <italic>
                        <sc>emlc</sc>
                    </italic>
                    , and the anonymous reviewers for reading and commenting on earlier versions of this article. The
                    code that was used in this study can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                                                                               xlink:href="https://github.com/awlassche/dutch-historical-song-topics">
                        https://github.com/awlassche/dutch-historical-song-topics
                    </ext-link> (accessed on 18 October 2022).
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
                <label>2</label>
                <p>Veldhorst, <italic>Zingend door het leven</italic>, 12.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
                <label>3</label>
                <p>Stronks, &#x2018;&#x200A;&#x201C;Dees kennisse zuldy te kope vinnen&#x201D;&#x200A;&#x2019;, 152.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
                <label>4</label>
                <p>Grootes, &#x2018;Het jeugdig publiek&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
                <label>5</label>
                <p>Stronks, &#x2018;Identiteiten van adolescenten&#x2019;, 225.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
                <label>6</label>
                <p>Stronks, &#x2018;&#x200A;&#x201C;Dees kennisse zuldy te kope vinnen&#x201D;&#x200A;&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
                <label>7</label>
                <p>Kestemont et al., <italic>Van wie is het Wilhelmus</italic>?
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
                <label>8</label>
                <p>Veldhorst, &#x2018;Pharmacy&#x2019;, 225-227.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
                <label>9</label>
                <p>Grijp, <italic>Het Nederlandse lied</italic>, 13.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
                <label>10</label>
                <p>Gelderblom, &#x2018;Investing in Your Relationship&#x2019;, 131.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
                <label>11</label>
                <p>Van Bork et al., <italic>Algemeen Letterkundig Lexicon</italic>, &#x2018;petrarkisme&#x2019;.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
                <label>12</label>
                <p>Grootes, &#x2018;Het jeugdig publiek&#x2019;, 84.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
                <label>13</label>
                <p>Grootes, &#x2018;Het jeugdig publiek&#x2019;, 85.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
                <label>14</label>
                <p>Keersmaekers, <italic>Wandelend in Den Nieuwen Lust-Hof</italic>, 119.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
                <label>15</label>
                <p>Van der Haven, &#x2018;Patriotism and Bellicism&#x2019;, 56.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
                <label>16</label>
                <p>Jensen (ed.), <italic>The Roots of Nationalism</italic>, 18.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
                <label>17</label>
                <p>Van der Poel, Grijp, and Van Anrooij, <italic>Identity, Intertextuality, and Performance</italic>, 4.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
                <label>18</label>
                <p>Van der Poel, Grijp, and Van Anrooij, <italic>Identity, Intertextuality, and Performance</italic>, 5.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
                <label>19</label>
                <p>Veldhorst, &#x2018;Pharmacy&#x2019;, 233.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
                <label>20</label>
                <p>Van der Poel, Grijp, and Van Anrooij, <italic>Identity, Intertextuality, and Performance</italic>, 8.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
                <label>21</label>
                <p>De Bruin, &#x2018;Het Wilhelmus tijdens de Republiek&#x2019;, 24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
                <label>22</label>
                <p>De Bruin, &#x2018;Het Wilhelmus tijdens de Republiek&#x2019;, 38.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
                <label>23</label>
                <p>Van Kranenburg, De Bruin, and Volk, &#x2018;Documenting a Song Culture&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
                <label>24</label>
                <p>This project involved cooperation between the <sc>dsd</sc> and the Digital Library of Dutch
                    Literature (<sc>dbnl</sc>), and was funded through a <sc>nwo</sc> Medium Investments grant.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
                <label>25</label>
                <p>Each first print of a song has a <italic>recordid</italic>, which is the id that is mentioned in the <sc>
                    xml
                </sc> file of a song. A reprint of a song does not contain a <italic>recordid</italic>, but a <italic>
                    herdrukid
                </italic> (<italic>reprintid</italic>) instead. Furthermore, each unique song has an <italic>
                    incnormid</italic>. This means that a couple of songs with different <italic>recordids</italic> and <italic>
                    herdrukids
                </italic> share the same <italic>incnormid</italic>. Songs with the same <italic>incnormid</italic> and/or <italic>
                    recordid
                </italic> as the ones already in the corpus were added.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
                <label>26</label>
                <p>In recent decades, more than 100 people (researchers, documentalists, interns, and volunteers) have
                    added metadata to the Dutch Song Database. This was mainly done within the context of a project, at
                    the Meertens Institute (which still hosts the database) and at other institutions such as the
                    University of Antwerp.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
                <label>27</label>
                <p>I have used a cut-off length of 1,000 words, since there was only a very small number of songs with a
                    bigger length.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
                <label>28</label>
                <p>Egghe and Proot, &#x2018;The Estimation of the Number of Lost Multi-Copy Documents&#x2019;; Proot and
                    Egghe, &#x2018;Estimating Editions on the Basis of Survivals&#x2019;; Proot, &#x2018;Survival
                    Factors of Seventeenth-Century Hand-Press Books&#x2019;.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
                <label>29</label>
                <p>Kestemont and Karsdorp, &#x2018;Estimating the Loss of Medieval Literature&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
                <label>30</label>
                <p>The current study only contains comparative analyses between topics belonging to the same genre.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
                <label>31</label>
                <p>Karsdorp, Kestemont, and Riddell, <italic>Humanities Data Analysis</italic>, 267.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
                <label>32</label>
                <p>Blei, Ng, and Jordan, &#x2018;Latent Dirichlet Allocation&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
                <label>33</label>
                <p>Pritchard, Stephens, and Donnelly, &#x2018;Inference of population structure&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
                <label>34</label>
                <p>R&#x00F6;der, Both, and Hinneburg, &#x2018;Exploring the Space of Topic Coherence Measures&#x2019;.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
                <label>35</label>
                <p>For a more comprehensible explanation of the method, see Syed and Spruit, &#x2018;Full-Text or
                    Abstract?&#x2019;.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
                <label>36</label>
                <p>For a detailed study on giving meaning to coherence values of topic models, see Uglanova and Gius,
                    &#x2018;The Order of Things&#x2019;.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
                <label>37</label>
                <p>The default parameters were used in all cases in which no parameters are reported.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
                <label>38</label>
                <p>An updated version, the <sc>vard</sc>2 tool, was used in this study.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
                <label>39</label>
                <p>Kisjes and Wijckmans, &#x2018;Adapting a Spelling Normalization Tool&#x2019;.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
                <label>40</label>
                <p>In my master&#x2019;s thesis, on which this article is based, I compared the results of three
                    versions of the corpus: the original version, the version that was normalized with a straightforward
                    script that used <sc>inl</sc> to normalize words, and the version that was normalized with the <sc>
                        vard2</sc>-tool. Both the results of the normalization and the coherence of the topic model
                    showed that the latter version of the corpus had the greatest research potential.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
                <label>41</label>
                <p>These were the words <italic>God</italic>, <italic>Gods</italic>, <italic>leven</italic>, <italic>
                    hert</italic>, <italic>ziel</italic>, <italic>liefde</italic>, <italic>tijd</italic>, <italic>
                    vreugd</italic>, <italic>here</italic>, <italic>geest</italic>, <italic>woord</italic>, <italic>
                    lief</italic>, <italic>min</italic>, <italic>kwaad</italic>, <italic>zonden</italic>, <italic>
                    heren</italic>, <italic>lof</italic>, <italic>hand</italic>, <italic>wereld</italic>, <italic>
                    mens</italic>, <italic>mensen</italic>, and <italic>recht</italic>.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
                <label>42</label>
                <p>The setting of this parameter was decided after calculating the coherence score of three topic models
                    with a no_below of respectively 2, 5, and 10. The topic model of no_below &#x003D; 2 gained the
                    highest coherence score.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
                <label>43</label>
                <p>The coherence score of the final topic model was 0.4962.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
                <label>44</label>
                <p>Note that py<sc>lda</sc>vis starts counting at 1, while the topics made with gensim start at 0. Each
                    number <italic>x</italic> in the py<sc>lda</sc>vis-plot therefore corresponds with topic id <italic>
                        x</italic>-1. Moreover, because py<sc>lda</sc>vis starts counting at 1, but gensim at 0, one
                    should add +1 to every topic. Topic 27 is therefore depicted as topic 28 in this visualization.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
                <label>45</label>
                <p>See for the appendix: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                                                   xlink:href="https://github.com/awlassche/dutch-historical-song-topics/blob/main/data/appendix.csv">
                    https://github.com/awlassche/dutch-historical-song-topics/blob/main/data/appendix.csv
                </ext-link> (accessed on 18 October 2022).
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
                <label>46</label>
                <p>I used a rolling average of twenty years in all graphs, to let &#x2018;accidental&#x2019; differences
                    between years have less impact on the analysis.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
                <label>47</label>
                <p>Hooft, <italic>Granida</italic>, 1.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
                <label>48</label>
                <p><italic>Een Nieu Geuse Lieden boecxken</italic>, no. 116.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
                <label>49</label>
                <p>Grootes, &#x2018;Liedjes over de Tachtigjarige Oorlog&#x2019;, 173.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
                <label>50</label>
                <p>Maertsz., <italic>Stichtelijcke gesangen</italic>, 200-201.
                </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
                <label>51</label>
                <p>Porteman et al., <italic>Een nieuw vaderland voor de muzen</italic>, 658-660.
                </p>
            </fn>
        </fn-group>
    </back>
</article>